Okay, so
好的，今天我们来讨论普京的计划，消灭美帝。
today we will discuss Putin's plan to destroy the American Empire.
在上一节课里我们讨论了……
So last class we discussed that
So last class wediscussed that
Putin loves his country, Russia,
普京热爱他的祖国俄罗斯，
and he believes that
并且他认为西方消费主义已败坏他的国家。
Western consumerism has corrupted his nation.
And he recognizes that
并且他认识到
the source of Western consumerism is the American Empire.
西方消费主义的源头是美帝。
So in order to completely free its people,
于是为彻底解放其人民，
he needs to destroy the empire.
他需要摧毁帝国。
And historically,
而且在历史上，
empires die when
帝国在...
three things happen concurrently, together.
三件事同时发生，合在一起。
The first is overextension.
第一件是过度扩张。
And this is the main reason why empires die,
这正是帝国衰亡的主要原因。
when they fight too many wars at once.
当他们一次打太多场战争时。
Okay. And the reason why they're overextended is hubris.
好的。它们过度扩张的原因是自负。
And what hubris is in military strategy is the idea of blindness.
在军事战略里，自负就是盲目。
So you are blind to the fact of your own limitations.
于是你对自身局限一无所知。
You are blind to the strategy of your opponents.
你对对手的战略一无所见。
You are blind to the overall geopolitical picture.
你对整体地缘政治图景一无所知。
Okay. You're just blind.
好的。你刚才才是盲目。
And the example is American strategy nowadays,
而例子是现在的美式战略，
where America is fighting Russia and Ukraine,
美国正与俄乌交战。
where it is fighting Hamas in Israel,
在以色列打哈马斯，
and there's a threat of Iran on the horizon.
还有伊朗的威胁在天际。
But for whatever reason,
但不管怎样原因，
most American policymakers believe
大多数美国决策者认为
that the real threat is China.
真正的威胁是中国。
We must prepare for China in Taiwan.
我们必须为中国在台湾做准备。
And if we don't, then Taiwan is straight. Okay?
如果我们不这么做，台湾就会直接落入手中。
Eventually, China will invade Taiwan, and we must be ready.
最终，中国会入侵台湾，我们必须做好准备。
Right now, this week,
现在这周，
America also announced massive tariffs on Chinese electrical vehicles.
美国还宣布对中国电动车征收大额关税。
And so America is engaged in all these wars at once.
于是美国同时卷入了所有这些战争。
It's antagonizing Russia,
它正与俄罗斯对峙，
Iran, China at the same time.
伊朗、中国同时如此。
And so that's just overextension because of hubris.
于是这就是因自大而导致的过度扩张。
Okay? Um, second,
好的？嗯，第二个，
second way to kill an empire is debt.
第二种消灭帝国的方式是债务。
So the source of American power is the US dollar.
于是美国力量的源泉是美元。
Remember that in 1945, Bretton Woods,
记住，1945年布雷顿森林会议，
there was an agreement that the US dollar would become the reserve currency of the world, okay?
那时约定美元成为世界储备货币，
And the word, the phrase for that is exorbitant privilege.
并且这个词、这个短语是“过度特权”。
Exorbitant privilege just means that
过度特权就是指……
America has the right
美国拥有从无中制造黄金的权利。
to manufacture gold from nothing.
而世界则必须去购买。
And the world has to buy it because
that's what underpins global trade.
这就是全球贸易的基础。
Okay? But when you can do that,
好吧？但当你能做到这一点时，
what happens eventually is that
最终会发生的事是
your nation becomes fat,
你的国家变得肥大，
rich, and lazy, and corrupt.
富裕，懒散，腐败。
When money just falls off the sky,
当钱从天而降时。
you're just used to borrowing money, okay?
你刚刚习惯借钱，行吗？
So all America does right now is print money and not make money.
于是美国现在做的事就是印钱不造钱。
The problem with this is that
这件事的难点在于…
eventually the world is not going to want the US dollars anymore
最终世界将不再需要美元
because each time you use it, you're being taxed, right, by the Americans.
每次使用美元，都是被美国人征税
And that's what breaks the law.
这就是破坏规律的原因
So what's the BRICS Plus? You may have heard of BRICS Plus.
那BRICS Plus到底是什么？你可能听说过BRICS Plus。
It is an organization established initially by Brazil,
它最初是由巴西、俄国、印、华、南组成的组织。
Russia, India, China, and South
Africa in order to create its
非洲为此创建自己的金融体系，以对抗美国金融体系。
own financial system to counter the US financial system.
但现在已有更多国家加入了金砖。
But now there are more countries that have joined BRICS.
Most prominently are Saudi Arabia.
最显著的是沙特阿拉伯。
And UAE and Bahrain.
以及阿联酋和巴林。
These countries, okay? They're important because they are the basis for the petrodollar.
这些国家，好的？它们之所以重要，是因为它们是石油美元的基础。
Remember that all US dollars can be used to purchase oil,
记住，所有美元都能买油，这就是美元价值高的原因。
and that's why US dollar is worth a lot of money, okay?
所以如果这些国家加入金砖，就会……
So if these countries go to BRICS and
opt out of the US financial system, then basically
退出美国金融体系，随后基本上是……
this American mountain of debt,
这座美国债务高峰，
okay, $3,500, $200 of debt comes crashing down.
好了，3500美元，200美元债务坍塌下来。
That's the second way to kill an empire. And
那是第二种消灭帝国的方法。然后
the third way is
第三种方法是
civil dissent or
内战或
eternal discord.
永恒的纷争。
Civil war, basically. And so
内战，基本上。于是
what we're seeing in America right now is growing political polarization,
我们现在在美国看到的就是政治极化的加剧。
okay, between the left and the right.
好的，左右之间。
Why this happens is that
之所以会这样是因为
people no longer believe the binding myths.
人们不再相信那种连结的神话。
Okay? And stories that
好的？还有那些建国的故事，好吗？
build a nation, okay?
现在的年轻人不再相信了。
Nowadays young people no longer believe that
Nowadays young peopleno longer believe that
America is the source of good in this world.
美国是这个世界的善源。
An example why this is happening is, of course,
这件事发生的一个例子，当然是，
because Israel right now is committing genocide
因为现在以色列正在实施大屠杀。
in Gaza. Right now Israel is attacking Rafa,
在加沙。现在以色列正攻击拉法，
and they're killing a lot of children.
他们正在杀死许多孩子。
Most people who are dying in this war are children.
这场战争中死去的多是孩子。
And America is not doing anything to stop this.
美国也没有做任何事来阻止这一切。
In fact, America is the one who is providing the issue of all the weapons.
事实上，美国才是把所有武器送到现场的那一方。
So young people are turning against the idea of America as the good empire.
于是年轻人开始把美国从善帝国的形象里抛出去。
And there's this amazing statistic that
还有一个惊人的统计数据
one quarter of young Americans now believe
四分之一的年轻美国人现在认为
that Osama bin Laden was a good guy.
奥萨马·本·拉登是个好人。
Okay? Okay? And, you know, when I grew up,
好的？好的？而且，你知道，当我长大时，
Osama bin Laden was considered Satan because
奥萨马·本·拉登被认为是撒旦，因为
he was the one who was responsible for terrorism around the world and for the 9 -11 attacks.
他是负责全球恐怖主义和9‑11袭击的人。
Okay? But this just shows you that
好的？但这只是向你展示
the ideas and the myths that bind the country together are falling apart.
想法与神话将国家团结在一起的东西正要散落。
And that's what's causing the nation to fall apart.
这就是导致民族国家分崩的原因。
Okay? So the more overcommitted America is,
好吧？美国越过度投入，
the more debt it creates
它产生的债务越多
and the more civil discord.
而且民间纷争越多
Okay? All right?
好吧？一切都好吗？
So this is how you kill an empire. When all three things reach a tipping point,
于是这就是消灭帝国的方法。当三件事都达到临界点时，
when it becomes too much, the empire dies.
当它过度时，帝国就会消亡。
Okay? And the most likely outcome for America is it goes into civil war.
好吧？美国最可能的结果就是内战。
Okay? It descends into civil war.
好吧？它降入内战。
And that's something that I will discuss next class.
这点我将在下节课讨论。
All right? So
好吧？于是
let's discuss how Putin is doing this.
让我们来讨论普京是怎么做的。
Okay? So the first thing that Putin did was the Ukraine war.
好吧？普京先做的事就是发动乌克兰战争。
Right? So in February 2022,
对吧？于是2022年二月，
Putin invaded Ukraine.
普京入侵乌克兰。
And at that time, America was confident
当时，美国很有信心
that three things would happen.
那三件事会发生。
Okay? The first thing that would happen is that
好的？第一件事会是……
Ukraine would destroy the Russian army
乌克兰将摧毁俄军
and perhaps even march to Moscow and overthrow Putin.
并且可能进军莫斯科，推翻普京。
Okay? At that time, that's what the news media was reporting.
好的？当时，新闻媒体就是这么报道的。
The Ukraine media was so much stronger and more confident.
乌克兰媒体更加强大，信心十足。
And the Russian forces.
以及俄军。
The second thing was that
第二件事是……
the Russian economy would be destroyed.
俄国经济将被摧毁。
Why? Because America was imposing sanctions on Russia.
为什么？因为美国对俄国实施制裁。
So America, because it controls the global financial system,
于是美国，因为它掌握全球金融体系，
the ability to trade,
拥有贸易能力。
America just basically sanctioned Russia and said,
美国刚刚对俄国实施制裁并说，
you are no longer allowed to sell your oil
你们不再允许出售油
on the black market.
在黑市上。
There was so much loss in the global market.
全球市场损失巨大。
There was so
有如此
much loss in the global supply chain.
全球供应链中有大量损失
There was so much loss in the global supply chain.
全球供应链损失巨大。
There was so much loss in the global supply chain. There was so much loss in the global supply chain. There was so much loss in the global supply chain. There was so much loss in the global supply chain.
全球供应链损失巨大。全球供应链损失巨大。全球供应链损失巨大。全球供应链损失巨大。
There was so much loss in the global supply chain. There was so much loss in the global supply chain. There was so much loss in the global supply chain.
全球供应链损失巨大。全球供应链损失巨大。全球供应链损失巨大。
There was so much loss in the global supply chain.
全球供应链损失巨大。
happened was that it would make NATO much stronger
那件事发生后，北约变得更强大。
and more united and
并更加团结
it would make Russia into a pariah state meaning
这将使俄罗斯成为流放国，意味着
that no one would want to ever associate with Russia again.
那时没有人愿意再与俄罗斯结缘。
Okay so that was the argument back
好的，回到那个论点
then and today what we have seen is
然后今天我们看到的是
that the complete opposite has happened.
那件事发生后，完全相反的事发生了。
Okay so
好了，回到那个论点。
first of all Russia has basically won the war
首先，俄罗斯基本赢得了战争
and it's won the war because of attrition right?
这场战争之所以赢得，是因为消耗战术吧
Ukraine has lost maybe 500,000 men in this war
乌克兰在这场战争中损失约五十万兵力
so they have no more manpower.
于是他们就没有足够的人力了
If you don't have manpower you're not going to be able to fight this war.
如果没有足够的人力，你就无法在这场战争中作战。
So this war has basically been lost and Russia is dominant.
于是这场战争基本上已失，俄罗斯则占据主导。
Russia has basically achieved its main strategic objectives
俄罗斯基本实现了其主要战略目标
which are which is basically the Donetsk region in eastern Ukraine.
即在乌克兰东部的顿涅茨克地区
Secondly, not only has the Russian economy not been destroyed
其次，俄国经济不仅没有被摧毁
but it's been doing extremely well okay
而且表现得非常好
and the reason why is that
原因就在于
ultimately all economies, China, India,
最终，所有经济体，像中国、印度、欧洲、非洲、中东，都需要资源才能让经济运转。
Europe, Africa,
Middle East, they all need resources in order for their economies to work.
最终，所有经济体，像中国、印度、欧洲、非洲、中东，都需要资源才能让经济运转。
You need oil, you need food.
你需要石油，你需要粮食。
And Russia has a lot of oil and food.
俄国有大量石油和粮食。
And that's why countries have been going to Russia
这就是各国去俄国的原因。
and making side deals.
并且做了边际交易。
Also, Russia has been transitioning to a war economy,
此外，俄国已转向战时经济，
so its manufacturing base has been increasing.
其制造业基地也在增长。
So overall, the economy has been doing a lot better.
整体来看，经济表现大幅提升。
U.S. sanctions have not been working.
美国制裁效果不明显。
The third of all, NATO has become more divided
第三点，北约内部分化加剧。
and less united.
并且更不统一。
Why? Because Germany,
为什么？因为德国，
which is the most powerful country in Europe right now,
它是目前欧洲最强大的国家。
is completely dependent on Russian
完全依赖俄方资源来驱动其经济。
resources to fuel its economy.
这就是德国经济的运作方式。
That's how the German economy works.
It's a manufacturing economy.
它是一个制造业经济体。
It takes cheap Russian gas,
它使用便宜的俄气，
manufactures it into cars, and sells it to China.
把它制造成汽车，再卖给中国。
But the United States blew up the North Sea.
但美国把北海炸了。
That's why it's completely dependent on Russian resources to fuel its economy. That's how the Germansaurium orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig
这就是德国经济完全依赖俄方资源来驱动其运作的方式。
orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig
orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig
orig
orig orig orig orig orig orig
orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig
orig
orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig been a tremendous success for Putin
……已成为普京的巨大成功
and it's really shown that America is a paper tiger
并且这确实显示美国是纸老虎
and it's also creating a lot of civil dissent in America
并且也在美国内部造成了大量民间纷争
because the majority of Americans are asking the
因为大多数美国人正在问
question why are we giving
问题是我们为什么在给
Ukraine hundreds of billions of dollars
乌克兰数百亿美元
when our people don't even have health insurance our people are suffering
当我们的人连医保都没有时，我们的人正在受苦
and we're giving Ukraine hundreds of billions of dollars.
并且我们给乌克兰数百亿美元。
The other thing that
另外一件事是。
this Ukraine war has exposed is
这场乌克兰战争所暴露的就是
that the American empire is overextended and what I mean by that
美国帝国已过度扩张，我的意思是
is that
是
in order to give Ukraine weapons what America
为了给乌克兰武器
is doing is basically taking weapon systems
正在做的基本是拿走武器系统
from in Japan in South Korea
从日本和韩国
and other places and giving it to Ukraine.
在其他地方也把它交给乌克兰。
So America is not manufacturing more weapons it's just taking other weapon systems and giving it to Ukraine.
于是美国不再生产更多武器，只是把其他武器系统拿走交给乌克兰。
It has elsewhere and moving it to Ukraine so
它在别处制造并转移给乌克兰。
America is badly overextended okay
美国已经过度扩张
and of course by giving all this money to Ukraine it's causing American debt to go up
当然，给乌克兰这么多钱也让美国债务上升
and after Ukraine loses war
乌克兰战败后
this debt will be gone okay because Ukraine cannot pay it back okay. So
这笔债务会消失，乌克兰付不回来。于是，乌克兰战争结束后，接下来发生的事是去年10月7日，哈马斯发动对以色列的进攻。
right after the Ukraine war what happened next was on October 7th of last year remember
在乌克兰战争结束后，接下来发生的事是去年10月7日，哈马斯发动对以色列的进攻。
that Hamas launched an attack on Israel
that killed about about a thousand people and
那场战斗造成约一千人死亡，且…
Israel responded by attacking Gaza
以色列随后对加沙发动攻击，…
and by doing this this has helped Putin
这一系列动作帮助普京完成…
and has hurt the United States okay.
并且伤害了美国。
Mainly by first of
主要是因为……
all diminishing American prestige right
所有这些都在削弱美国的声望。
because America right now is helping Israel commit genocide
因为现在美国正在帮助以色列实施种族灭绝
so the entire world is basically turning against America.
于是整个世界基本上都转向了美国。
Even the young people in America are turning
甚至美国的年轻人也在转向。
against America you know these college protests
在美国，大学抗议会在秋季进一步扩大。
in America they will only expand in the fall okay.
And the other problem is
还有一个问题是
that America has shown it cannot control Israel in fact people say
美国已经证明它无法控制以色列
that Israel now controls America and
那以色列现在掌控美国，且
the third thing is that this war threatens to explode.
第三点是这场战争即将爆发。
There's so much origination around the Middle East so the origination around the Middle East so the origination around the Middle East so
有这么多的起源在中东，起源在中东，起源在中东
the origination around the Middle East so
起源在中东
the origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East
origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East
起源在中东
origination around the Middle East origination around the
起源在中东起源在中
Middle East origination around
中东起源
the Middle East
中东
knew about the Hamas attack
知道哈马斯袭击的事
or even encouraged the attack, okay?
甚至鼓动了袭击，行吗？
Because the main winner of the Hamas attack is obviously Vladimir Putin,
因为哈马斯袭击的主要赢家显然是弗拉基米尔·普京，
and the loser is America, okay?
而输家则是美国，行吗？
So does this make sense so far?
那么到目前为止，这样说通吗？
All right, so
好的，接下来是
let's talk about the future or what are predictions moving forward.
让我们谈谈未来，或者说说向前的预测。
So if it is true that
那么如果真的是这样的话。
Putin's intention is to destroy the
普京的意图是毁灭
American Empire by focusing on
美国帝国，聚焦于
these three fundamental weaknesses in the Empire,
这些帝国的三大基本弱点，
and if it is true that
如果这是真的的话
he started the Ukraine war to further
他发动乌克兰战争是为了进一步使帝国衰落
the deterioration of the Empire, if he is one
如果他是那种扶持哈马斯的人
who is abetting Hamas, then
who is abettingHamas, then
we can predict that Putin will continue to destroy the American Empire.
我们可以预测普京会继续摧毁美国帝国。
So if it is true that Putin's intention is to destroy the American Empire, then we can predict that Putin's intention is to destroy the American Empire. certain things, okay? The first thing that
于是如果普京的意图确实是摧毁美国帝国，那么我们可以预测普京的意图就是摧毁美国帝国。先说几件事，好吗？第一件事是
he will do is he will
他将要做的第一件事是
drag on the Ukraine war.
拖延乌克兰战争。
So he will not end it,
于是他不会结束它，
he will not seek peace,
他也不会寻求和平。
he will not negotiate peace terms, he will continue to drag it on,
他不会谈判和平条款，他会继续拖延它。
okay? Why would he do that?
好？他为什么要这么做？
Why not just declare victory?
为什么不直接宣布胜利呢？
Or why not just negotiate peace?
或者直接谈判和平？
Why would he do that? Why not just declare victory? Or why not just negotiate peace? orig Why would he want to drag it on?
他为什么要这么做？为什么不直接宣布胜利？或者直接谈判和平？
Okay, yeah, the Russian people will constantly be at war, but
好的，俄国人民会一直处于战争之中，
then the question then is, why would he drag it on and not expand it, right?
然后问题是，为什么他要拖延而不扩张，没错吗？
He wants to drag it on, but he doesn't want to expand it.
他想拖延，却不想扩张。
Expand it means he attacks Poland.
扩张就是攻击波兰。
He doesn't want to do that, he just wants to drag it on.
他不想这么做，只是想拖延而已。
Why? Yeah,
为什么？嗯，
okay, so the reason is that
好，原因是这样。
Ukraine is turning out to be a black hole for NATO.
乌克兰正变成北约的黑洞。
NATO and the United States is putting in all this money,
北约和美国投入了大量资金、武器和人力。
weapons, and manpower,
and it's just losing it all, okay?
并且它正全失，好的？
So, in other words,
所以，换句话说，
Ukraine is a battlefield to increase American debt
乌克兰是提升美债的战场
and create civil discord among NATO and America, okay?
并在北约与美之间制造内战，好的？
Germany does not want to fight this war.
德国不想再打这场战争。
Germany wants out, you understand?
德国想退出，你懂吗？
So as long as this war keeps on going,
只要这场战争继续下去，
it's gonna create more friction between NATO and the United States, and that's what Putin wants.
它会在北约与美国之间产生更多摩擦，而这正是普京想要的。
But if Putin attacks Poland,
但如果普京进攻波兰，
then all NATO is forced to fight him, okay?
然后所有北约都被迫去跟他打仗，好的？
Does that make sense? So he does not want to expand the war,
这样说通吗？所以他不想把战争扩大，
he just wants the war to maintain a status quo and
他只是想让战争保持现状，
for it to drag on, okay?
为了让它持续下去，好的？
So that's the first prediction.
于是这是第一个预测。
Second is that
第二个是……
to control the situation in Ukraine,
为掌控乌克兰局势，
he needs America to fight another war, okay?
他需要美国再打一场战争，好吗？
He needs to distract America, and the distraction will be Iran.
他需要分散美国，目标是伊朗。
Remember how, for the past few classes,
记得吗，过去几节课我们讨论过美国想攻击伊朗的情形。
we've been discussing how America wants to attack Iran and
Iran wants revenge against America, okay?
伊朗想要报复美国，好吗？
But for this to happen, what Putin needs to do is talk to Iran
但要实现这一点，普京需要做的就是与伊朗对话。
and guarantee that
并保证
Iran will be protected by the Russian nuclear umbrella.
伊朗将被俄方的核伞所保护。
Which means that
这意味着
America will not be allowed to use nuclear weapons
美国将不被允许使用核武器
when it invades Iran, because
当它入侵伊朗时，
Putin will respond with nuclear weapons of his own, okay, does that make sense?
普京会用自己的核武器回应，好吗？这样说对吗？
So as long as Putin comes to an agreement with Iran
只要普京与伊朗达成协议
and say that, I will use my nuclear weapons to protect you from US nuclear weapons,
并说我会用核武器保护你免受美方核武器
then Iran will take the initiative
然后伊朗将主动出击
and start to provoke America into a wider war.
随后伊朗会挑起美方更大规模的战争
And again, there are many ways Iran can do that, okay?
再说一次，伊朗有多种方式可以做到这一点，好吗？
It can use Hezbollah to attack Iran, to attack Israel,
它可以利用真主党攻击伊朗，也攻击以色列，
it can expand its nuclear program,
它可以扩充核计划
it can disrupt Red Sea shipping, okay?
它可以扰乱红海航运，行吗？
There are lots of ways that
有多种方式可以用来
Iran can use to provoke America into a full -scale invasion,
伊朗用来挑起美方的全面入侵
which is what Putin wants, all right?
这正是普京想要的，行吗？
North Korea. So,
北韩。于是，
as the United States becomes distracted in Ukraine
当美国在乌克兰分心时
and Iran, North Korea can now take the initiative, right?
伊朗、北韩此时可先发制动，行吗？
Because what North Korea can do is threaten to invade South Korea.
北韩可先发威胁入侵南韩。
And there are about 30,000 US troops in South Korea.
还有大约三万美军驻扎南韩。
So North Korea doesn't actually have to do anything, but
于是北韩其实不必做什么，但……
the threat of North Korea will force
北韩的威胁将迫使……
America to divert resources to South Korea.
美国将把资源调往韩国。
Does that make sense? Okay? And
这有道理吗？好吧？然后
this will probably even have to force South Korea in the United States to start to bribe North Korea.
这可能甚至会迫使美国开始向北韩行贿赂。
Okay? And we can expect that
好吧？然后我们可以预期……
North Korea does this because
北韩之所以这么做是因为……
Putin has given North Korea his assurance
普京已向北韩作出保证
that he will protect North Korea in the event of a war.
他会在战争发生时保护北韩。
Okay, does that make sense? All right, BRICS.
好吧，这有道理吗？好的，BRICS。
We will see BRICS continue to expand,
我们将看到BRICS继续扩张。
okay? We will also see BRICS maybe formally announce
好吧？我们还会看到BRICS可能正式宣布
a new currency or a new trading system to counteract, okay?
一个新货币或新的贸易体系来对抗，好吧？
Whether the US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или
无论美元还是美元还是美元
US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US
美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元
dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или
美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或美元或
US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или
美元或美元或美元或美元
US dollar или US dollar или US dollar
美元或美元或美元
или US dollar или US dollar или you will no longer want to use it okay does
或美元或美元或你将不再想使用它，好吗？
that make sense and
那有道理吗？
um the last thing is to maintain
嗯，最后一件事是保持
close relationships to maintain maintain a very close relationship with china
保持与中国的非常密切关系
so putin will come to china more often
所以普京会更频繁地来访中国
and he and xi jinping will hug each other more okay they might even kiss one day
他和习近平会更频繁地拥抱，甚至可能会在某天亲吻
who knows okay but and
谁知道呢，嗯，还有…
again listen the reality is if you look at game
再说一次，现实是如果你观察游戏
theory there are lots of geopolitical differences between russia
理论上，俄罗斯和中国之间有很多地缘政治差异，远比中美之间多
and china much more so than between china united states
但再次说，普京……
but again putin that
but again putinthat
doesn't actually need china to do anything all putin
不需要中国做任何事，普京只需要中国不再与美国合作
needs is for china not to work united states okay
因为在这种情况下，只有一种方式…
because in this situation one way
because in thissituation one way
that the united states can survive or protect its
美国能存活或保其帝国，就是与中国合作
empire is by working with china
正好以此三角化对俄
right to triangulate against russia does that make sense
这样说对吗
so as long as china remains neutral then
只要中国保持中立，……
russia and putin can continue to exert pressure on the american empire
俄国和普京可以继续对美帝国施压，……
okay so
好了，接下来……
over the next three to four years we should see all these things happen okay
在接下来的三到四年里，我们应该看到这些事都发生，好吗？
so first thing is the ukraine war does not end putin will find a way for it to drag on
首先是乌克兰战争，没完，普京会让它继续拖延，实际上还会扩张。
but actually expanding okay that's the first
这就是第一点。
thing second thing is iran um
第二点是伊朗，嗯
takes the initiative against united states third thing is that the united states is going to be a very important part of the united states and the united states is going to be a very important part of the united states and the third thing
第三点是美国将成为美国的重要组成部分，且美国将成为美国的重要组成部分，第三点是北朝鲜开始对南朝鲜更具战斗性
is north korea starts being becoming much more belligerent against south korea
第三点是北朝鲜开始对南朝鲜更具战斗性
and japan forcing america to focus more attention
以及日本让美国更加关注东亚
in east asia briggs will continue continue to expand
在东亚的布里格斯将继续扩张
uh and then the putting relationship with cdp will continue to blossom okay does that make sense
然后与CDP的关系将继续繁荣，明白吗？
all right any questions so far before i continue
好的，先问问，先到这儿还有问题吗？
excuse me okay
请问一下，好的。
that's a good question so
这是个好问题。
why would america want china's help okay the
为什么美国想要中国的帮助？
first thing is you have an over extension problem okay
第一点是你有过度扩张的问题。
you don't want to be fighting too many wars at once so
你不想一次打太多场战争。
you come to a piece of china you don't have to worry about east asia anymore
你来到中国后，东亚不再是你需要担心的地方
because the real threat from america's perspective is
因为从美国的角度来看，真正的威胁是
that china invades taiwan okay that's the
中国入侵台湾
first thing okay second thing is that
第一件事，第二件事是……
china is a major buyer of u.s dollars
中国是美国美元的主要买家
because because of its trade with america
因为与美国的贸易……
and because china buys our oil right you want china to keep on buying u.s dollars
并且因为中国买我们的油，你想让中国继续买美元
so you can sustain the debt okay does
于是你可以维持债务，行吗？
that make sense and
这样说对吗？
third of all there are a lot geopolitical conflicts between russia
第三个，所有的，俄罗斯和中国之间有很多地缘政治冲突
and china
if you think about it russia is more of
如果你想想看，俄罗斯更像是……
a threat to china than united states is okay
……对中国的威胁比美国更大，好的
Does that make sense? Historically, Russia and China fought wars,
这有道理吗？历史上，俄罗斯和中国曾多次交战，在边境上打过多场战争。
many wars, over the border.
多场战争，在边境上打过多场战争。
So if you become friends with China,
如果你和中国结成朋友，
then Putin needs to take the defensive and
那么普京就得转为防御。
focus more on protecting the Russia -China border.
聚焦于保护俄中边境。
Does that make sense? Because right now, Putin can just focus on the offensive,
这有道理吗？因为现在，普京可以只聚焦进攻。
but if China's on the side of the United States, then Putin is forced on the defensive.
但如果中国站在美国一边，普京就被迫转为防御。
Does that make sense? Any more questions, yeah, Peter?
这有道理吗？还有问题吗，彼得？
China's done a lot of this US funds.
中国已经做了很多这类美金。
That's right. And they've made it.
对，没错。并且……
That's right, that's right. So basically,
没错，没错。所以基本上，
what's been happening is China is
正在发生的事是中国在
now no longer buying US dollars.
现在不再买美元了。
And it's transferring its US dollars into gold, okay?
并且把美元换成金，行吗？
So China's encouraging everyone to buy gold.
于是中国鼓励大家买黄金。
Don't buy any more US dollars, guys, buy gold.
别再买美元了，大家买黄金。
And the reason why is because America's debt
而原因是因为美国的债务
is a huge problem.
是个大问题。
There's so much loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss
有这么多的损失
loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss
损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损失损
loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss for China
and the United States to be friends, right?
美国也要跟中国做朋友，对吗？
Because China exports a lot of commodities to the United States.
因为中国向美国出口大量商品。
The United States is a huge market.
美国是一个巨大的市场。
The United States also provides China with a lot of technology, right?
美国也为中国提供了大量技术，对吗？
And Jack asked the question, why would China want to be friends with Russia?
于是杰克问了一个问题：为什么中国想跟俄罗斯做朋友？
And the answer is because China right now
答案是因为中国现在觉得被美国威胁，好的？
feels threatened by the United States, okay?
The United States is launching an economic war against China.
美国正对中国发动经济战争。
And if you look at a map,
如果你看一张地图，
okay, China is surrounded by US military bases.
好的，中国被美军基地包围。
And the problem is that
问题是……
China needs imports of oil
中国需要进口石油
and food to sustain its economy.
以及食品来支撑其经济。
Does that make sense? So
这有道理吗？
if America ever launches a embargo against China,
如果美国曾对中国实施禁运，
China collapses, okay?
中国崩溃，好吗？
So in other words, China needs to open up new trade routes.
换句话说，中国需要开辟新的贸易路线。
And the best partner right now is Russia because
而现在最好的合作伙伴是俄罗斯，因为
it has a lot of access to energy and oil, okay?
它有很多能源和石油的渠道，好吗？
So right now, the situation in China is
现在，中国的局势是
that Chinese policymakers know that the situation in China is terrible.
那时中国决策者已知局势惨烈。
The economy has collapsed.
经济已崩溃。
Demographics has collapsed.
人口结构已崩溃。
China is completely dependent on the world for oil.
中国完全依赖世界的石油。
China is extremely vulnerable right now.
中国现在极为脆弱。
If America says to the world, China is our enemy,
如果美国对世界说：‘中国是我们的敌人’
then China has no choice but to find a new friend.
然后，中国只能再找一个新朋友。
And unfortunately, the only friend that China has right now is Russia, okay?
而且不幸的是，现阶段中国唯一的朋友就是俄罗斯，行吗？
Does that make sense? Okay.
这有道理吗？行吗？
So, but look,
于是，先说一下，
I mean, the geopolitical situation for China, it's really, really bad, okay?
我想说的是，中国的地缘政治形势真的非常糟糕，行吗？
Any more questions before I continue?
还有问题吗？
Okay. Okay,
好的。
so, Selena asked a great question. Why does the United States think
于是，塞莱娜提出了一个很好的问题。美国为什么认为中国会攻击台湾？
that China will attack Taiwan?
答案是：美国总是想发动新战争，行吗？
And the answer is that
而答案是，美国总是想发动新战争，行吗？
America is always looking to start new wars, okay?
美国总是想发动新战争，行吗？
It has something called a military -industrial complex.
它有一个叫做军工复合的东西。
And America is always fighting wars.
美国总是打仗。
So to justify all this defense spending,
为此，美国需要为这笔防御开支做辩护，
it needs to find new enemies.
它需要再找新的敌人来支撑，
And it believes that
于是它便认为……
the greatest threat to the American empire right now is China,
目前美国帝国最大的威胁是中国，
even though, by the way, there's no evidence this is the case, okay?
顺便说一句，没证据表明如此，
Right now, the relationship between the United States and
现在美中关系是……
China is China sends America a lot of cheap goods
中国向美国发送大量低价商品
and the US gives China a lot of US dollars,
美国则给中国大量美元
okay? So basically what's happening is
好吧？基本上发生的事是
that the Communist Party is storing the wealth of the Chinese people
共产党把中国人民的财富存入美国银行。
in American banks. This is a great deal for both America,
这对美国、华尔街和中国共产党都是一笔大交易。
Wall Street, and the Chinese Communist Party, okay?
好吧？
So there's no reason for these countries to be in conflict with each other,
于是这些国家之间没有必要相互冲突，
but unfortunately, the American policymakers
但不幸的是，美国决策者
always need an enemy to justify the
总是需要一个敌人来证明
incredible amount of money they spent on defense, okay?
他们在防御上花了不可思议的金额，行吗？
Does that make sense? Okay, any more questions before I continue?
这样说对吗？好了，继续之前还有别的问题吗？
Excuse me?
请问一下？
I didn't understand the question.
我没听懂问题。
Can you repeat that?
请再说一遍。
The United States is not trying to attack Taiwan
美国并未打算攻台。
and the US is very interested in China.
美国对此非常关注。
Oh, that's a great question. So
哦，这是个好问题。于是……
what happens if China takes over Taiwan?
如果中国接管台湾会怎样？
What does America lose? And the answer is not that much, okay?
美国失去什么？答案并不多，行吗？
You can make the argument that China takes over Taiwan that Taiwan has a semiconductor industry,
你可以说中国接管台湾后，台湾拥有半导产业，
but guess what? You can move that semiconductor industry elsewhere,
但你猜怎么？你可以把半导产业搬到别处，
okay? For America, it's just one of face, you understand?
好吧？对美国来说，这只是面子的一部分，你明白吗？
America doesn't really lose anything if China takes over Taiwan,
美国若中国接管台湾，实际上并未失去什么，
but for America, it's the empire.
但对美国而言，那就是帝国。
It has hubris, and therefore, it must save face,
它自负之气，因此要保住面子
right?
对吗？
Does that make sense? All right, all right.
那有道理吗？好了，好的。
So this is Putin's plan.
于是这就是普京的计划。
To destroy the American empire.
毁灭美帝国。
And so the question then is,
于是问题是，
well, this makes Putin a genius.
好，这让普京成为天才。
So how is he able to do this?
那么他是怎么做到的？
And the argument I want to make to you today is
我今天想给你们说的论点是
that for many reasons,
因为有很多原因，
Russian leaders have a strategic imagination.
俄国领导人有战略想象力。
They just think differently.
他们只是思考方式不同。
And more strategically than anyone else, okay?
更具战略性胜过其他人，好的？
And so the example I want to use is Joseph Stalin.
我想用的例子是约瑟夫·斯大林。
Because we actually know a lot about Joseph Stalin.
因为我们确实了解很多关于约瑟夫·斯大林的事。
All right, so let's look at the world in 1939.
好了，接下来我们来看看1939年的世界。
And in 1939, there are about six global powers, okay?
在1939年，全球大约有六个大国，好的？
There's Soviet Union, okay?
有苏联，好的？
There's Japan. There's United States.
有日本。有美国。
There's Britain. There's UK, Britain, the British empire,
有英国。英国、英国帝国、英联。
Germany, and France, okay?
德国和法国，好的？
So this is the map of the world in 1939.
这就是1939年的世界地图。
Now, let's talk about each country.
现在，让我们谈谈每个国家。
United States is far away, and it's neutral.
美国很远，且处于中立状态。
It does not like to get involved in affairs of Europe.
它不喜欢介入欧洲事务。
But it's suffering from the Great Depression.
但正遭受大萧条的打击。
Its economy has collapsed, okay?
其经济已崩溃，好的？
Japan, the Japanese empire, is a war machine.
日本，日帝国，是一台战争机器。
But the problem for Japan is that
但日本面临的问题是……
it is completely reliant on imports,
它完全依赖进口，好的？它需要油来支撑帝国、战争机器。
okay? It needs oil for its empire, its war machine.
还有只有两个近处的油源。
And there are only two sources of oil close by.
And there are only twosources of oil close by.
There's the Soviet Union far east,
有远东的苏联，
and then there's Southeast Asia, okay?
然后是东南亚，好的？
Now, Japan is getting most of its oil
现在，日本正从油里得到大部分
from the United States.
来自美国。
But the United States is angry at Japan.
但美国对日本很生气。
Why is the United States angry at Japan?
美国为什么对日本生气？
Do you guys know? Exactly, okay, because Japan invaded China.
你们知道吗？对，好的，因为日本入侵中国。
And the United States doesn't want that, okay?
美国也不想这样，好的？
So it's very likely that
很可能是这样。
the United States will eventually cut off all exports to Japan.
美国最终会把所有出口给日本断掉。
And so Japan has a choice.
于是日本有了一个选择。
You can either invade here, or you can invade here.
你可以先进攻这里，或者再进攻这里。
But those are your two choices, okay?
但那就是你的两个选择，好的？
That's Japan. You can either invade the Soviet Union or Southeast Asia.
那是日本。你可以进攻苏联，也可以进攻东南亚。
Okay, the Soviet Union is a communist country.
好的，苏联是个共产国。
Okay? And for the past 20, 30 years,
好的？过去20、30年间，
it's been trying extremely hard to industrialize.
它一直非常努力工业化。
But it's hard to industrialize because,
但工业化很难，因为，
first of all, no one wants to trade with the Soviet Union, okay?
首先，没有人想与苏联做贸易，好吗？
So they can't get any resources.
于是他们就拿不到任何资源。
The Soviet Union is still very much an agricultural nation.
苏联仍然是一个以农业为主的国家。
And the Soviet Union doesn't really have that much technology and expertise,
苏联技术和专业水平不算高，
okay? Doesn't really have that much human capital.
好吧？人力资源也不算多。
So the Soviet Union, it's a huge country.
苏联是个大国。
It's a huge country. It's an empire.
它是一个大国，也是一个帝国。
But in terms of manufacturing and technology, it's behind the West, okay?
在制造业和技术方面，它落后于西方，好吗？
Now in Europe, there are three nations.
在欧洲，已经有三国。
You have France, Germany, and the UK.
法国、德国和英国。
The UK is an empire, okay?
英国是一个帝国，好吗？
It has colonies all around the world.
它在世界各地都有殖民。
Germany lost World War I,
德国在第一次世界大战中失去领土，
and so it has to pay all these reparations to UK
于是它必须向英国和法国支付全部赔款，
and France, okay?
好吗？
And now Hitler is in power.
现在希特勒掌权。
And Hitler is determined to reunite Germany,
希特勒决意统一德国，行吗？
okay? Because Germany lost a lot of land because of World War I, okay, so
因为德国在第一次世界大战中失去大量领土，行吗？
he wants to reunite greater Germany, okay?
他想统一大德国，行吗？
That's his ambition. It's not to conquer the world, it's to reunite Germany.
这就是他的雄心。不是要征服世界，而是要统一德国。
All right? And then you have France,
好了？然后你就有法国，
which is the weakest of all these powers,
哪一个是这几大国中最弱的，
but it still has an empire, okay?
但它仍然有一个帝国，行吗？
So looking at a map in 1939,
于是我们看着1939年的地图，
and we use game theory,
我们用博弈论来分析，
what should be happening, or what should happen maybe five years from now, 1945,
接下来应该发生的事，或者说五年后，也就是1945年的事，
okay? Let's use game theory to map out what should be happening,
好了？我们用博弈论来绘制应该发生的事
or what will happen, given this map,
或者会发生什么，基于这张地图，
and given the individual players, the interests of these different nations.
以及各个玩家、各国的利益，
What do you expect to happen? What does everyone hate?
你预期会怎样？大家又都嫌谁？
Who does everyone hate? Who does everyone want to go invade?
谁是大家都嫌的？谁是大家都想去侵略的？
Why? Why does everyone want to invade the Soviet Union?
为什么？为什么大家都想侵略苏联？
Okay, yes, first of all, it has a lot of resources, and it's not that strong,
好的，首先，它资源丰富，而且实力不算强大。
okay? That's the first reason, but there's actually a better reason why, okay?
好的？这就是第一个原因，但实际上还有更好的理由，好的？
Everyone wants to attack the Soviet Union.
大家都想攻击苏联。
Why? What's happening internally in the United States right now?
为什么？美国内部现在发生了什么？
The Great Depression. What ideology is a threat to the American government?
大萧条。哪种意识形态对美国政府构成威胁？
Communism, okay, do you understand? So
共产主义，好吗，你懂了吗？
there's a global communist movement in the 1930s that's very,
1930年代有一个全球性的共产主义运动，十分…
very powerful. In fact, in the 1930s, and
非常强大。事实上，在1930年代，和
you guys don't know this, but America was on the brink of revolution, okay?
你们不知道这点，但美国正处于革命边缘，行吗？
The communists could have any time took
共产党人随时都能夺取
over America if America failed to stop the economic bleeding
若美国未能止住经济流失，便会落在美国之上
that was happening, all right?
那时正在发生，没错吧？
So everyone was afraid of communism.
于是大家都怕共产主义。
Japan would have loved to invade Soviet Union because Japan hates communism,
日本本来就想入侵苏联，因为日本恨共产主义。
and Soviet Union has a lot of oil, right?
和苏联有很多油，对吧？
So here comes Japan.
于是日本来了。
Germany would love to destroy the Soviet Union because
德国本来就想毁灭苏联，因为
Nazis hated who the most?
纳粹最爱恨谁？
Who did Nazis hate who the most?
The Nazis. Why did they hate Jews? Why did they hate Jews?
纳粹为什么最爱恨犹太人？
What did Hitler believe about Jews?
希特勒认为犹太人是什么？
Okay, they controlled the world economy, but there's actually a better reason why he hated Jews.
好的，他们掌控世界经济，但更好的理由是他为什么恨犹太人。
What was the problem with Jews? Okay,
犹太人有什么问题？好了，
you guys don't know this, but they were all communists, okay?
你们不知道这点，但他们全是共产主义者，好的？
Hitler thought that all Jews were communists.
希特勒认为所有犹太人都是共产主义者。
So Hitler hated, first and foremost, communism, okay?
于是希特勒首先最爱恨共产主义，好的？
Not so much communism. Marxism hated communism the most.
不只是共产主义。马克思主义最爱恨共产主义。
So Hitler wanted to invade the Soviet Union.
于是希特勒想入侵苏联。
How about France and the UK? How about France and the UK?
法国和英国呢？法国和英国呢？
What did they want to do? Who did they hate?
他们想干什么？他们恨谁？
Russia, right, Soviet Union.
俄国，对吧，苏联。
United States, sure, why not, okay, do you understand?
美国，当然，为什么不呢，好吗，你明白了吗？
So 1945, if we just game theory, okay,
于是1945，如果我们只用博弈论，好吗？
we should have expected that
我们本来应该预料到
Soviet Union would have been partitioned into different countries.
苏联会被分割成若干国度
These powers would have invaded the country together
这些大国会联手入侵该国
and colonized the Soviet Union
并殖民化苏联
and destroyed the threat of global communism once and for all.
并彻底消灭全球共产主义的威胁
Does that make sense? But that's not what happened.
这有道理吗？但那不是事实。
What happened was
发生的事是
that in 1939,
在1939年
Hitler invaded Poland.
希特勒入侵波兰
The moment that Hitler invaded Poland,
当希特勒入侵波兰之时，
France and Britain declared war on Germany.
法国和英国对德国宣战。
And then Germany defeated France and Britain.
随后德国击败法国和英国。
Britain was forced to return to Europe.
英国被迫回到欧洲。
Britain was forced to return to its island. But
英国被迫回到自己的岛屿。但
Churchill refused to seek peace with Hitler.
丘吉尔拒绝与希特勒求和。
In fact, Hitler tried to seek peace with Churchill seven times.
实际上，希特勒七次尝试与丘吉尔和解。
And each time Churchill was like, go to hell.
每一次丘吉尔都答曰：去死吧。
We're going to fight this war to the end.
我们将把这场战争打到底。
Why was Churchill so angry at Hitler?
为什么丘吉尔对希特勒如此愤怒？
What happened? I don't know.
发生了什么事？我不知道。
I don't know. I don't know. I don't know.
我不知道。我不知道。我不知道。
Because Germany destroyed the British army, right?
因为德国打败了英国军队，对吧？
It's a complete loss of face for the British empire.
这对英国帝国是一次完整的丢面子。
So Churchill was very, very angry at Hitler.
于是丘吉尔对希特勒非常非常愤怒。
And Churchill refused to ever negotiate with Hitler.
于是丘吉尔始终不与希特勒谈判。
In fact, Hitler sent this emissary called Rudolf Hess to Britain,
实际上，希特勒派遣了名为鲁道夫·赫斯的特使去英国，
to Scotland, to negotiate a truce.
再去苏格兰，去谈和约。
And Churchill just put him in prison.
于是丘吉尔把他关进了监狱。
Okay? But,
好？不过，
he didn't. So, what's the irony of all this?
他没这么做。那这其中的讽刺是什么？
Germany invades Poland.
德国入侵波兰。
Why does Germany invade Poland? Do you guys know?
德国为何入侵波兰？你们知道吗？
Have you guys studied this history?
你们学过这段历史吗？
Okay. It's because
好的。那是因为……
of something called the Molotov -Rippentrop Pact.
某个叫做莫洛托夫-里宾特洛普条约的东西。
So this was an agreement between the Soviet Union
于是这就是苏联之间的协议。
and Germany to partition Poland into two.
德国把波兰分成两部分。
Do you understand? So, Germany
你明白了吗？于是德国……
and the Soviet Union invaded Poland together.
德国和苏联一起入侵波兰。
Soviet Union attacked from the east,
苏联从东部进攻，德国从西部进攻。
and the Germans attacked from the west.
但实际发生的是，英国…
But what happened was, Britain
and France declared war on Germany, but not the Soviet Union.
法国向德国宣战，但向苏联未宣战。
Okay? That's pretty clever of Stalin, don't you think?
好吧？斯大林真是机智，您觉得呢？
In fact, you can make the argument that
实际上，您可以这样论证：
if this thing was not signed,
如果这件事没签署，
then the Soviet Union would not have attacked Poland.
那么苏联就不会进攻波兰。
And the reason why is, the other thing about this pact is that
而且之所以如此，另一个关于此协定的要点是：
Soviet Union agreed to give Germany resources for its war machine.
苏联同意向德国提供战争机器所需资源。
Oil and food and other inputs.
石油、粮食及其他投入。
Okay? Does that make sense? Because, remember,
好吧？这有道理吗？因为，记得，
the Soviet Union has the Ukraine, which produces a lot of food and oil.
苏联拥有乌克兰，乌克兰产粮食与石油。
Okay? Does that make sense? All right?
好吧？这有道理吗？行吗？
Next thing that happened was that in June, 1936, the Soviet Union was in power.
接下来发生的事是，1936年6月，苏联掌权。
In 1941, Operation Barbarossa.
1941年，巴巴罗萨行动。
So Hitler invades the Soviet Union.
于是希特勒入侵苏联。
Okay? And if you read history,
好吧？如果你读历史，
anyone will tell you that
有人会告诉你
this Operation Barbarossa was a tremendous success for Germany
这次巴巴罗萨行动是德国的巨大成功
and a strategic failure for the Soviet Union.
是苏联的战略失误。
It was a great mistake, strategic blunder for Stalin.
那是一次大错，斯大林的战略失误。
Okay? What did Stalin do wrong? Well, first of all,
好吧？斯大林犯了什么错？首先，
he refused to defend the border.
他拒绝了边境防御。
Okay?
好的？
There were 45 million Soviet troops at the border defending the Soviet Union.
当时有4500万苏军驻守边境，保卫民族国家。
But they were given direct orders to not, to not,
但他们收到直接命令：不……
to not, sorry, given direct orders not to provoke the Germans.
给出直接命令不去挑衅德国人。
You understand? The Germans fire at you, don't fire back.
你明白吗？德国人向你开火，你不还手。
And because of this order.
正因如此命令。
The German army, which was about three to four million,
德国军队约有三到四百万人，
was able to overrun the border and almost reach Moscow.
能够冲过边境并几乎抵达莫斯科。
Okay? That was a great mistake on the part of Stalin.
好吧？这对斯大林来说是大错。
Second is that Stalin ignored intelligence.
第二点是斯大林忽视情报。
Okay? There was a lot of intelligence that said that
好吧？有大量情报说德国要进攻苏联。
Germany was going to invade the Soviet Union.
德国即将入侵苏联。
How could you hide the fact that
你怎么能把四百万人军队集结进攻苏联的事实藏起来？
you have four million troops assembled to attack the Soviet Union?
好吧？于是有大量情报送到斯大林手里。
Okay? So there's a lot of intelligence going to Stalin and
telling Stalin, hey, the Germans are coming.
告诉斯大林，嘿，德军来了。
And Stalin said, nope, I refuse to believe this intelligence.
斯大林说，没，我不相信这份情报。
In fact, you had German soldiers desert the German army,
实际上，你让德军士兵从德军中叛逃。
swim across the river to the Soviet side
游过河到苏联岸边
and tell the Soviets, hey, my comrades,
告诉苏联人，嘿，我的同志们，
the entire army is about to attack you.
整个军队即将来袭击你们。
And the Soviets shot these German soldiers
苏联人把这些德军士兵射了出去
because they thought these German soldiers were spies.
因为他们以为德军士兵是间谍
Okay? So
好吗？
Stalin ignored intelligence.
斯大林忽视情报。
The third thing that Stalin did was,
斯大林第三件事是，
before the outbreak of war,
在战争爆发之前，
he purged the Red Army,
他清洗了红军
the Soviet Army, of its leadership,
苏军的指挥部队
of general orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig
将其将帅清洗
orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig prison
监狱
because Stalin got rid of them for not being politically loyal enough.
因为斯大林把他们除掉是因为他们政治上不够忠诚。
But the fourth thing is why did Stalin do this?
但第四件事是：为什么斯大林会这么做？
And the answer is, what historians will tell you is that
而答案是，历史学家会告诉你的事是：
Stalin trusted Hitler.
斯大林信任希特勒。
This was the ultimate mistake that Stalin made.
这就是斯大林犯下的终极错误。
Stalin believed Hitler was his friend.
斯大林认为希特勒是他的朋友。
He believed that Hitler would never invade him.
他认为希特勒永远不会进攻他。
So this is what you're taught in history class.
这就是你在历史课上学到的内容。
When you go to the United States, you'll be taught this.
当你去美国时，你会被教到这一点。
When you go on the internet, you'll be taught this.
当你上网时，你会被教到这一点。
This is completely wrong.
这完全是错的。
This analysis is completely wrong.
这项分析完全错误。
So we're going to use game theory to understand why this is wrong.
于是我们将用博弈理论来理解它为什么错
So using game theory, let's look at four possible scenarios.
于是用博弈理论，来看看四种可能的情景。
Scenario A is Soviets attack first,
情景A是苏联先发攻击
and they encircle Berlin.
并包围柏林。
Second scenario is Soviets attack,
第二个情景是苏联发动攻击
and they're stopped at the border.
并在边境停下。
Scenario C is Germans attack,
情景C是德国人发动攻击
and the Soviets stop them.
并且苏联将其阻止。
Scenario D is Germans attack,
情景D是德国人发动攻击
and they reach Moscow, which is actually what happened.
并且他们抵达莫斯科，这正是实际发生的情况。
So these are four possible different scenarios
于是这四个可能的不同情景
that could have happened in June 1941.
那可能在1941年6月发生过。
Remember that
记住
there were four to five million Soviet troops at the border.
边境有四到五百万人驻军
What were they doing there?
他们当时在做什么？
They were about to attack Germany.
他们正准备攻击德国。
The Soviets had a plan to attack Germany,
苏联曾计划先攻德国，但德国先发制人。
but the Germans struck first.
but the Germansstruck first.
So let's look at these four possible scenarios and see what happens.
于是我们来看看这四种可能的情景，看看会怎样发展。
First scenario is the Soviets attack Germany first, and they reach Berlin.
第一种情景是苏联先攻德国，然后到达柏林。
What happens now? What happens now?
现在会怎样？现在会怎样？
What do all the other countries do?
其他各国会怎样做？
Yes, do you understand?
是的，你明白了吗？
Stalin reaches Berlin, and he's going to attack Moscow.
斯大林抵达柏林，随后向莫斯科发动进攻。
And then, boom, Japan comes from the east.
然后，咚咚，日军从东边来袭。
Britain comes to the aid of Germany.
英国援助德国。
The United States comes to the aid of Britain.
美国援助英国。
All the world unites against the Soviet Union.
全世界统一对抗苏联。
Okay? So
好的？那么
what would happen in this war?
这场战争会怎样发展？
The Soviet Union loses this war.
苏联在这场战争中败北。
Do you understand? Okay? Now let's look at B.
你明白了吗？好吧，现在我们来看看B。
The Soviets invade,
苏联发动进攻，
and they stop them at the border.
并在边界将其阻止。
Okay? Now what happens?
好吧？现在发生了什么？
Now what happens?
现在发生了什么？
Yeah, so Japan still invades.
是的，日军仍然进攻。
Okay? And Britain starts to negotiate with Germany
好吧？英国开始与德国谈判，寻求和平。
and seek a peace. Because
因为
Britain cannot afford for the Soviet Union to overrun Germany,
英国不能让苏联占领德国，否则共产主义将统治欧洲。
because then communism takes over Europe.
这有道理吗？好吧？
Does that make sense? Okay?
So in B, we can't say that
于是B中，我们不能说苏联会输，但也不会赢得战争。
the Soviet Union would lose, but they would not win the war.
好吧？你明白吗？B也不算好。
Okay? Do you understand? So B is not that good either.
Okay? Do you understand? SoB is not that good either.
And let's look at C. The Germans attack,
再看C。德国人发动进攻，
and the Soviets hold them at the border. Now what happens?
苏联在边境迎击。接下来会怎样？
Now what happens? They just destroy each other,
随后会怎样？双方互相消灭。
right? The United States, Britain, Japan, they're all laughing.
对吧？美国、英国、日本，他们都在笑。
They're like, oh, they're just killing each other. Who cares?
他们说，噢，彼此互相消灭就行。谁在乎？
Not a problem. Okay? But
没问题。好了？
now let's look at situation D, where the Germans attack,
再看D局面，德国人发动进攻，
and they are about to destroy the Soviet Union.
他们即将消灭苏联。
What happens now? The other countries have to come
接下来会怎样？其他国家得赶来。
and help the Soviet Union.
并帮助苏联。
Why? Why is it the United States and
为什么？为什么美国和英国必须来帮助苏联？为什么？
Britain must come to help the Soviet Union? Why?
What would happen if Germany takes over the Soviet Union?
如果德国占领苏联会怎样？
Why would they take over the Soviet Union? That's right.
他们为什么要占领苏联？对吧。
Okay? They take over the resources, therefore they take over the world.
好的？他们夺取资源，随后就掌控全世界。
You understand? Because Germany has technology, it has military power,
你明白吗？因为德国有技术，有军力，
but it lacks resources. You combine the resources with the German military,
但缺乏资源。你把资源与德国军力结合起来。
they're invincible now. The United States will be forever shut out of the world.
他们现在无敌可战。美国将永远被排除在世界之外。
The United States will be forever shut out of the world. Germany will not invade the United States, but the United States will never ever attack Germany again.
美国将永远被排除在世界之外。德国不会入侵美国，但美国再也不会进攻德国。
Does that make sense? So
这有道理吗？
what happens is after the Soviets invade,
发生的是苏联入侵之后，
sorry, after the Germans invade, and the Soviet army is destroyed,
抱歉，德国入侵后，苏军被消灭，
America immediately gives the Soviet Union a lot of aid.
美国立即向苏联提供大量援助。
America immediately gives the Soviet Union a lot of aid. America immediately gives the Soviet Union a lot of aid. It's what we call land lease.
美国立即向苏联提供大量援助。美国立即向苏联提供大量援助。这就是我们所说的陆权租赁。
1941 to 1945,
1941年至1945年
America gave 200 billion dollars to the Soviet Union for free.
美国向苏联免费送出2000亿美元。
to the Soviet Union for free. It gave weapons,
随后又送去武器。
resources, technology, and food to the Soviet Union.
资源、技术和粮食送给苏联。
Basically, what America did was
基本上，美国所做的就是
industrialize the Soviet Union.
工业化苏联。
Does that make sense? That's what America did.
这样说对吗？这就是美国所做的。
The Soviet Union could not industrialize by itself, but
苏联自己没能工业化，但美国帮助苏联工业化。
America helped the Soviet Union to industrialize.
美国帮助苏联工业化。
Let's look at land lease, okay?
看一下陆权租赁，好吗？
Weapons. America gave the Soviet Union one third of all ammunition used in the war.
武器。美国给了苏联三分之一的战时弹药。
One third of all explosives.
三分之一的所有炸药。
One half of all aircraft.
一半的飞机。
One half of all aircraft. 14,000 airplanes.
一半的飞机。14,000架飞机。
One half of all tanks.
一半的坦克。
13,000 tanks.
13,000辆坦克。
America gave oil and food.
美国送油送粮。
80% of all copper.
80%的铜。
55% of aluminum
55%的铝
and steel. Technology.
和钢铁。技术。
America gave the Soviet Union radio technology,
美国送给苏联无线电技术。
radio communications, railroad, transportation,
无线电通信、铁路、运输
heavy industry, and lots and lots of food.
重工业，和大量的粮食。
In other words,
换句话说，
America basically built the Soviet Union in heavy industry for it,
美国基本为苏联建造了重工业，怎么样？
okay? Does that make sense?
这样说对吗？
And also, at the end of the day,
又，到了最后，苏联可以做的事是把这些技术反向工程化。
what the Soviet Union can do is reverse engineer all this technology
and build its own industry.
并自行建造工业。
Does that make sense? Okay?
这样说对吗？
So, land lease really turned
于是，陆权租赁真正把苏联变成了超级大国。
the Soviet Union into a superpower.
And Stalin could get all this for free because
而且斯大林能免费得到这一切，因为
America could not afford for the Soviet Union to lose the war.
美国无法让苏联输掉战争
Okay? What's the other benefit of having the Germans attack first
好吧？让德国人先发动攻击有什么其他好处？
and almost destroy Moscow?
并几乎摧毁莫斯科？
What's the other benefit? And Stalin really needed this.
还有什么好处？而斯大林确实需要它。
This is actually more important than land lease. Which is what?
这实际上比陆权租赁更重要。那是什么？
National unity. Right?
全国统一。对吗？
Now all the Soviets were united in the fight against
现在所有苏联人都在对抗战中团结一心
Nazi Germany. Before communism was tearing the country apart,
纳粹德国。共产主义把国家撕裂之前，有一场内战。富人们都离开了国家，对吧？
there was a civil war. The rich people all fled the country, right?
But now because the Germans were invading,
但现在因为德国入侵，整个国家团结起来对抗德国。
the entire country was united against Germany.
the entire country wasunited against Germany.
This is what they call the Great Patriotic War.
这就是他们所说的伟大卫国战争。
They were fighting this war for the love of their country.
他们为祖国之爱而战。
The love of Mother Russia.
对母亲俄罗斯的热爱
Okay? So, and
好的？那么，
what turned the war was the way the Germans had the will to fight.
决定战争走向的是德国人那种有斗志的方式。
The Russians lost 26 million people in the war.
俄罗斯人在战争中损失了2600万名人。
That's a lot of people. But by losing this many people, it made the entire nation
那可是很多人。但失去这么多人，整个国家就……
refuse to surrender. They had the will to fight.
不投降。他们有斗志。
Okay? Much more so than the Germans.
好的？比德国人多得多。
Does that make sense? Okay?
这样说对吗？好的？
So in history, you're taught that Operation Barbarossa
于是，在历史上，你们学到巴巴罗萨行动证明了斯大林不是战略天才。
proved that Stalin was not a strategic genius.
proved that Stalin wasnot a strategic genius.
That he was
那他是
played by
由
Hitler. But if you just do game theory analysis,
希特勒。但如果你只是做博弈论分析，
this was the best possible outcome for the Soviet Union.
这就是苏联最好的可能结果。
Okay? In 1939,
好的？1939年，世界本该统一对抗苏联。
the world should have united against the Soviet Union.
But what happened was the world united against Nazi Germany
但发生的事是世界统一对抗纳粹德国
and gave the Soviet Union the technology, the money,
并给了苏联技术和资金
and the resources to become a global superpower.
并拥有资源成为全球超级大国。
Right? Does that make sense?
对吗？这有道理吗？
And because the Soviet Union became a global superpower,
因为苏联成为全球超级大国，
it was able to turn China
它能够把中国变成一个共产主义国家。这样说对吗？
into a communist country. Does that make sense?
如果苏联没有成为全球超级大国，拥有所有这些重工业，...
If the Soviet Union did not become a global superpower with all this heavy industry,
then China would not become a communist power.
那么中国就不会成为共产主义大国。
Moscow would not have won the war.
莫斯科也不会赢得战争。
Okay? So
对吗？
in other words, all this is telling us is that
换句话说，这一切告诉我们的就是
Stalin is a genius.
斯大林是个天才。
He turned a losing war into a winning war.
他把一场败战变成了胜战。
Okay? So the last thing I want to do is Okay, fine.
对吗？所以我想做的最后一件事是，好的，没问题。
How was Stalin able to do this?
斯大林是怎么做到的？
What makes the Russian imagination
是什么让俄罗斯的想象力如此强大？
different from the Western imagination?
不同于西方的想象力吗？
Okay? So I would say three things.
对吗？所以我想说三件事。
The first thing is just intuition.
第一件事就是直觉。
And intuition means that Putin and
并且直觉意味着普京和斯大林能读懂政治风向。
Stalin they're able to read the political winds.
他们能读懂政治风向。
They're able to sense the mood of the world.
他们能感知世界的气氛。
The German word for this is Zeitgeist.
德语里这个词叫Zeitgeist。
Spirit of the times.
时代精神。
But they're able to sense
但他们能感知。
the mood of the world.
世界的气氛。
Putin knows that the American empire
普京知道美帝国即将消亡。
is about to die. And so he feels important to act.
于是他觉得行动至关重要。
Okay? So it's intuition. Second is imagination.
好的？所以是直觉。第二个是想象。
So Putin and Stalin both have a strategic imagination.
所以普京和斯大林都有战略想象。
Which means like, okay, they sense these winds, but they can also imagine,
也就是说，他们感知这些风向，却也能想象。
hey, if I did this, how would these winds change?
嘿，如果我这么做，风会怎么变？
Okay? That's an imagination.
好？这就是想象。
Or imagine the future. And
或者想象未来。
the last thing, which is the strangest of all,
最后一件事，最奇怪的，是多重人格。
is multiple personalities.
就是多重人格。
Meaning that Putin and
即是普京和
Stalin are such brilliant men that
斯大林是如此出色的人
they embody multiple personalities in them.
他们在其中体现了多重人格。
And that's why they're so unpredictable.
这就是它们如此难以预料的原因。
Alright? So the example is this.
好了？那么例子就是这个。
Everyone says that
大家都说。
Stalin trusted Hitler.
斯大林信任希特勒。
So Hitler played Stalin.
于是希特勒扮演了斯大林。
But if you just look at,
但如果你只看一看，
if you just analyze the game, okay, then the conclusion is Stalin played
如果你只分析这场游戏，好的，那么结论是斯大林扮演了
Hitler. You understand?
希特勒。你明白吗？
Hitler did everything
希特勒做了一切事
that Stalin wanted him to do.
那是斯大林想让他做的事。
Hitler invaded Poland, which caused
希特勒入侵波兰，导致
France and Britain to declare war on him.
法国和英国向他宣战。
Okay? Then Hitler attacked Soviet Russia,
好的？随后希特勒袭击苏联。
which brought America into the war
这把美国拖入战争
and helped the Soviet Union become an empire.
并帮助苏联成为帝国。
You understand? So Hitler was completely played by Stalin.
你明白了吗？于是希特勒完全被斯大林操纵。
And the answer is, so the question then is, how?
答案是，问题是，怎么做？
Because in 1941,
因为在1941年，
June 1941, Hitler did not have to invade
1941年6月，希特勒本可以等着再进攻苏联。
Soviet Union. Okay? He could have waited
好吧？
for Stalin to invade him.
为斯大林进攻他。
Then the opposite would have happened.
然后相反的事就会发生。
Then America would have joined the war on Hitler's behalf.
然后美国会代表希特勒参战。
And they would have defeated the Soviet Union.
随后他们会击败苏联。
Okay? So
好的？那么
what convinced Hitler to do the most insane thing
是什么让希特勒做出最疯狂的事
and invade Russia first?
先进攻俄国吗？
And the answer is,
答案是，
Hitler trusted Stalin.
希特勒信任斯大林。
Does that make sense? Alright?
这有道理吗？好吧？
So imagine this. Hitler and Stalin, they're having drinks.
想象一下：希特勒和斯大林在喝酒。
Okay? They're both drunk. And
好的？他们都喝醉了。然后
they're on the porch and they're staring at the mountains and the moon.
他们在门廊上，凝视着山峦与月亮。
Okay? And Stalin and Hitler are talking.
好的？斯大林和希特勒正在交谈。
And all Stalin has to do is say three words.
而且斯大林只需说三句话。
And then Hitler is like, I'm gonna come and invade you. What are these three words?
随后希特勒会说：我要来侵略你。那三句话是什么？
How can Stalin get Hitler to invade Russia?
斯大林怎样让希特勒入侵俄罗斯？
What are the three words that
这三句话是什么？
Stalin can say to Hitler?
斯大林可以对希特勒说？
I trust you.
我信你。
Okay? I, Joseph Stalin, trust you out of Hitler.
好的？我，约瑟夫·斯大林，因希特勒而信你。
I don't trust anyone. I don't trust my own mother.
我不信任何人，我连自己的母亲也不信。
But I trust you, Hitler. Okay?
但我信你，希特勒。好的吗？
Then why would Hitler invade?
那为什么希特勒要入侵？
Exactly. Okay? Because Hitler
正是。好的吗？因为希特勒
thinks now that Stalin is his target.
现在认为斯大林是他的目标。
As Jacques says. Stalin is a sheep.
正如雅克所说。斯大林是羊。
I, Hitler, am a lion.
我，希特勒，是狮。
I am a wolf. You are a sheep.
我是一只狼。你是一只羊。
Therefore I eat you. You understand?
于是我吃掉你。你明白吗？
Okay? And, but
好的？还有，然而
Stalin could only do this if he had multiple personalities.
斯大林只有在多重人格的情况下才会这么做
Okay? Stalin
好的？斯大林
had to be a sheep in front of Hitler.
他必须在希特勒面前装作羊。
He couldn't pretend. He had to be.
他没能假装，必须真装。
Does that make sense? Okay?
这有道理吗？好吗？
So this is, these three things
所以这就是，三件事
are the Russian strategic
是俄罗斯战略
imagination. The ability to feel the political winds of the moment.
想象力。感知当下政治风向的能力。
The ability to prophesize and predict.
预言与预见的能力。
The ability to be multiple individuals at once.
一次能成为多重个体的能力。
And that's how Stalin was able to win World War II.
于是，斯大林得以赢得第二次世界大战。
And this is why Putin will be able to destroy
这就是普京能打败美国帝国的原因。
the American Empire. Okay?
好了？
Any questions? Okay.
还有问题吗？好的。
So Stalin asked the most important question.
于是，斯大林提出了最重要的问题。
Why are the Russians different?
为什么俄罗斯人不同？
Okay. Alright. So
好的。好了。于是
the problem isn't Russia.
问题不在于俄罗斯。
The problem is us.
问题在于我们。
The West. Okay? So
西方。好的？于是
when we talk about the West, Western thinking,
当我们谈到西方，西方思维时，
it comes from British thinking.
它来自英国思维。
And there are three distinct
并且有三种不同的
characteristics of British thinking that's different from Russian thinking.
英国思维的三大特点，区别于俄国思维。
Okay? Alright. Let's look at
好的？好了。我们来看看
British philosophy versus Russian philosophy.
英国哲学对比俄国哲学
Alright? Okay.
好了？好的。
The first major difference is that
第一个主要区别是
British philosophy tends to be narrow.
英国哲学往往狭窄。
Whereas Russia tends to be broad.
俄国哲学则宽广。
Okay? The reason why is Britain is an island.
英国是岛屿，故而如此。
Therefore it thinks very narrowly about the world.
因此它对世界的思考非常狭窄。
Whereas Russia is a huge country.
而俄国则是一个大国。
It's the world's largest country. Therefore it thinks very broadly about the world.
它是世界上最大的国家，因此它对世界的思考非常宽广。
And to understand the difference, what you do is you read British literature
要理解差异，你先读英国文学
and compare it with Russian literature.
再与俄国文学对照。
Okay? Russian literature, you have war and peace.
俄国文学有《战争与和平》。
And these are very huge
而这些都是非常巨大的史诗。然后
epics. And then
英国文学里有简·奥斯汀、托马斯·哈代。
British literature, you have Jane Austen, Thomas Hardy.
They're great. Okay? But they're very narrow in their focus.
它们很棒。好吧？但聚焦很窄。
So that's the first big difference.
这就是第一个大区别。
Second big difference is
第二个大区别是
British philosophy believes in the idea of
英国哲学相信怀疑主义的观念。好吧？而且
skepticism. Okay? And
帕拉索姆是英国哲学家如大卫·休谟所发展出的哲学。
Parasome is a philosophy developed by British philosopher like David Hume.
Parasome is a philosophy developed byBritish philosopher like David Hume.
And the idea is we can only know
并且想法是我们只能知道
what we experience.
我们能知道的只是我们所经历的。
We can only know what we see.
我们只能知道我们所见的。
Okay? So another word for Parasome is the idea of skepticism.
好的？所以“帕拉索姆”还有一个词是怀疑主义的观念。
Be skeptical of abstract philosophy.
对抽象哲学保持怀疑。
Okay? Because we can never know it.
好的？因为我们永远不知道它。
For example, you can never really understand mathematics because
例如，你永远无法真正理解数学，因为
mathematics is beyond your experience.
数学超出你的经验范围。
Okay? You can only know what you experience.
好吧？你只能知道你所经历的。
Okay? And it's true.
好的？而且确实如此。
But it's very but it limits your imagination.
但它确实很……但它限制了你的想象。
Okay? The Russians believe in mysticism.
好吧？俄罗斯人相信神秘主义。
Okay? So they're very spiritual
好吧？于是他们很有灵性
religious people. So
宗教人士。于是
there are forces we don't understand.
有些力量我们尚未理解。
There are individuals who are prophets who
有些人是先知
are sent to us by God.
由上帝送达我们
We can never know who they are.
我们永远不知道他们是谁。
We can never know how they think. But we just have to believe that's the case.
我们永远不知道他们是怎么想的。但我们只需相信就是这样。
Okay? So the Russians are going to be much more mystical
好的？所以俄罗斯人思考会更具神秘色彩
in their thinking than the British are.
Okay? And the last thing is
好的？最后一点是
the British believe in logic.
英国人相信逻辑。
Okay? It's like mathematics. You can go from one to two to three to four to five.
好的？就像数学。你可以从一到二到三到四到五。
Okay? Everything has to be logical.
好的？一切都要有逻辑。
Everything has to be connected together.
一切都要相互连贯。
Whereas the Russians, they believe in intuition.
而俄国人则相信直觉。
Okay? You can jump.
好的？你可以跳跃。
You can imagine things.
你可以想象事物。
You don't have to be logical. Whereas the British say you have to be logical.
你不必逻辑化。英国人则认为必须逻辑化。
And these three ideas, neural, empiricism,
以及这三点：神经、经验主义、
and logic, they created the western
以及逻辑，他们创造了今天的西方思维。
mind of today.
好吧？这就是学术界的主导。
Okay? So this is what dominates in academia.
Okay? So this is whatdominates in academia.
So when you go off to university, they expect you to think in this way.
于是你去大学时，他们期望你以这种方式思考。
Neural, empirical, and logical.
神经、经验、逻辑。
Okay? And if you think about it, this is perfect if you want to build a bureaucracy.
好吧？如果你思考它，这正是你想建造官僚的完美方式。
Right? This is bureaucratic thinking.
对吧？这就是官僚式思维。
This is the bureaucratization
这就是官僚化
of the imagination.
想象的
Okay? You're not allowed to
好的？你不可以随便说话，必须有证据、逻辑与经验。
say things without evidence and logic and experience.
Okay? And the Russians
好吧？而且俄罗斯人没有这个。于是他们可以做到这一点。
don't have this. So they can do this.
Alright? Now,
好的？现在，有明显比这套系统更好的东西。
there's obviously more good things about this system than about this system. But
但
the problem with the British system is like no great man could ever arise
英国制度的问题在于没有伟人能从中诞生
from western society.
来自西方社会。
Does that make sense? Because all this creates a
这有道理吗？因为这一切都产生了一个
process -orientated, systemized, bureaucratic
以过程为导向、系统化、官僚化
thinking. Okay?
思考。好吗？
So, for example,
比如说，
I give this talk, right?
我给这场演讲，行吗？
I could never give this talk in America or Britain
我在美国或英国从来没能给这场演讲
because they would all think I'm crazy.
因为他们都以为我疯狂
Okay? Does that make sense? They're like, what's your evidence for this?
好吗？这样说通吗？他们会问，凭什么说的？
Wait, are you refuting
等一下，你是在反驳关于二战的十年研究？
decades of scholarship about World War II?
Are you telling me that Stalin
你是说斯大林吗
was a genius when no one thought he was a genius?
在他被认为是天才之前
How dare you
你怎么敢
refute these thousands of scholars
反驳这些千名学者
who have put all this work into World War II scholarship?
谁把这所有工作投入到二战学术研究中？
Okay, do you understand? Alright?
好的，你明白了吗？好吧？
So, in the British system, no one like Putin can arise.
所以，在英国体系里，像普京那样的人不会出现。
But, in the Russian system, someone like Stalin and Putin can arise.
但在俄国体系里，像斯大林和普京那样的人可以出现。
The problem though is that what happens if you don't have
问题是，如果没有普京或斯大林会怎样？
Putin or Stalin? Well, then you're, you're, you're, then
嗯，那你就会是、你就会是、你就会是、然后
this system, this system becomes very weak.
这个体系，这个体系变得很弱。
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay?
好吧？这样说通吗？好吧？
So, the British system doesn't really need great leaders.
所以，英国体系确实不需要伟大领袖。
The Russian system, you do need great leaders.
而俄国体系则需要伟大领袖。
And if you are a great leader, then you are allowed to completely
如果你是伟大领袖，那么你可以完全依赖直觉与想象去做大事。
follow your intuition and imagination to do great things,
随后你可以全然凭直觉与想象去完成伟业。
like Joseph Stalin in World War II and what Putin is doing today.
像约瑟夫·斯大林在第二次世界大战中的表现以及普京今天的所作所为。
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay.
好吧？这样说通吗？好吧？
Any more questions? Oh, that's a great question.
还有问题吗？哦，这是个好问题。
Okay? So, last semester we said the Greeks.
好吧？所以，上学期我们说的是希腊人。
And the Greeks
以及希腊人
are more like the Russians than they are like the British.
希腊人更像俄国人，而非英格人
Okay? So,
好吧？所以，
the Russian system, the Greek system, it's a much more natural human system.
俄国系统、希腊系统，更自然的人类系统。
Okay? And the British system
好的？英国体系呢？
basically, it's trying to remove intuition and imagination
基本上，就是把直觉和想象去掉。
from the decision making process, from the intellectual process,
从决策过程，从智力过程，
because intuition and imagination
因为直觉和想象
are too mysterious.
太神秘了。
Okay? So, in other words, okay, let's just say that I'm Joseph Stalin in
好吧？换句话说，好的，我就是约瑟夫·斯大林。
World War II, okay, 1939.
第二次世界大战，好吧，1939。
For me to execute my plan, I need to write a memo
为了执行我的计划，我需要写一份备忘录。
detailing my thinking.
详细阐述我的思路。
Okay? Now, obviously I can't do that, because if I did that,
好吧？现在，显然我做不到，因为如果我做了，
first of all, I couldn't execute my plan, but second,
首先，我没能执行我的计划，但其次，
it would confuse everyone. Like, what are you trying to do again?
然后，大家会被搞糊涂。你又想干什么？
Okay? Do you understand? Okay?
好吧？你明白了吗？好吧？
And so, the Greeks believed in imagination and intuition as well.
于是，希腊人也相信想象与直觉。
Okay? But not the British. And we live in a British system.
好吧？但不是英国人。我们生活在英国体系里。
Okay? All right? Any more questions?
好吧？没错？还有别的问题吗？
Okay, so, Jack asked a good question, okay?
好，杰克问了个好问题，好吧？
How, like, how much did the Greeks influence the British?
那，希腊人到底影响了英国人多少？
And the answer is not that much, because remember, like, after the Greeks came, the Romans.
答案是影响不大，记得，希腊人来后，罗马人又来。
The Romans were like this.
罗马人就是这样。
And it was the Romans who influenced the British, who then influenced the Americans.
于是罗马人影响了英国人，随后又影响了美国人。
Okay? So we're living basically in a Roman world as opposed to a Greek world.
好吧？所以我们基本上生活在罗马世界，而不是希腊世界。
Right? Does that make sense? Okay.
对吧？这样说通吗？好吧。
Any more? Okay. So, any more questions?.
还有吗？好吧。那，另外还有问题吗？
..
…
So, um,
那，呃，
this is a really hard question, okay?
这是个很难的问题，好吗？
What influences Russia?
是什么影响了俄罗斯？
Well, I mean, what the Russians will say is that they're a Christian nation.
嗯，我是说，俄罗斯人会说他们是个基督教国家。
That they come from a Christian
那是来自基督教传统的。并且基督教传统又来自希腊传统，好吗？
tradition. And the Christian tradition comes from a Greek tradition, okay?
好吗？听得懂吗？
Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay? Does thatmake sense?
So, Christianity, um, Christianity,
所以，基督教，呃，基督教，
they would say that Christianity
他们会说基督教
is the main influence, okay?
是主要影响，好的？
And there's some Greek elements to Christianity.
还有一些希腊元素在基督教里。
What the Russians say is that their Christianity is a more
俄罗斯人说他们的基督教更像是……
pure, or more ancient form of Christianity, okay?
更纯粹，或者更古老的基督教，好的？
Because remember, like, when we study Christianity,
因为记得，像，学基督教时，
Christianity changed over the centuries, right?
基督教在几个世纪里变了，没错吗？
So, basically, this is a pre -Augustine Christianity,
所以，基本上，这就是奥古斯丁之前的基督教。
okay? Before Augustine..
好的？在奥古斯丁之前…
Any more questions?.
还有问题吗？
Okay, great. So, um,
好的，太好了。
next class we do the American Civil War, okay?
下节课我们来讲美国内战，好吗？
..
…